在你来这儿之前
Before you came to the city,
我祈求诸神把我从主人手里
I prayed to the gods that they would deliver me
解救出来
from the hands of my Dominus.
诸神回应了我的祈祷
And in you my prayers were answered.
想还债 就离我远点
Then see it repaid, by staying far from my presence.
以及像我这样的人
And men of my kind.
斯巴达克斯从希留爱沙山释放了一些俘虏
Spartacus releases a clutch of prisoners from Sinuessa.
你帮助那个杀死你丈夫的人
You gave aid to the man that robbed you of husband's life,
就为了自保
in order to save your own?
就算重来一次 我还是会这样做
A thing I would do again, if so needed.
你父亲爱你 提比略
Your father loves you, Tiberius.
不 他夺走了我的东西
No, he took something from me.
那我也要夺走他的东西
And I would have something in return.
抱歉了 兄弟
Apologies, brother.
我也不希望你落到这个下场
I did not wish you such an end.
我们中计了
We are betrayed!
我们要打开城门 夺回这座城
We must see gate opened and city retaken!
该死的叛徒
Fucking traitor.
不 是该死的罗马人
No, I'm fucking Roman.
《斯巴达克斯：诅咒者之战》
《战利品》
我不是说了 你们该逃跑了吗
Did I not tell you that you should run?
我们必须守住城门
We must hold the gate!
敌人太多了
There are too many!
撤退
Fall back!
欢迎来到希留爱沙城
Welcome to Sinuessa.
这些人是从哪儿涌进来的
Where did fucking these appear from?
城门被攻下了
The gate has fallen!
我们被出卖了
We have been betrayed.
操
Fuck!
我真是愚蠢 竟然信任赫拉克里奥
I stand eternal fool for laying trust in Heracleo.
赫拉克里奥
Heracleo?
背叛我们的是莱西克斯
It was Lyciscus that turned upon us.
他是个该死的罗马人
He stands fucking Roman.
狗日的
Fucking shit!
所以他才会帮那些西利西亚人
That is why he aided the Cilicians.
他们也背叛我们了吗
They have fucked us as well?
纳西尔去哪儿了
Where is Nasir?
和卢戈一起去提醒大家了
Dispatched with Lugo to call warning.
我必须找到他
I must find him.
通知大家向北门撤退
Carry word to break for northern gate.
我们必须确保剩下的人安全撤到山上
We must see all that remain to safety of the ridge.
你想让我们逃跑吗
You would have us run?
我是想保全大家的命
I would have us live.
那我们必须战斗 守住这里
Then we must fight and make our stand here
克拉苏现在占据上风
Crassus has seized the moment.
我们还不足以直接与他兵戎相见
We are not prepared to face him in the streets.
我们的人还没等撤出北门
Nor will our numbers pass through northern gate
他就能打过来了
before he descends upon them.
我来引开他们 争取一点时间
I will cause distraction, and gain needed time.
你打算怎么做
By what means?
我还没想好
I have no fucking idea.
不 和他们一起撤吧
No, move with the others,
我去把罗马人引开
I will draw the Romans away
我这不是请求
This is not request!
你是他们的领袖
You lead these people.
如果你死了 那将是致命的损失
If you were to fall it would be fatal blow.
我死了 没多少人在乎
My passing of lesser concern.
我很在乎
Of concern to me.
甘尼克斯
Gannicus
快走
Go!
等我完事了就去找你
I will find you when it is done.
我们会尽量等你的 兄弟
We shall wait as long as we are able, brother.
你个疯子
You mad fuck.
- 千万不要死 - 你也是
- Do not die. - Nor you.
快跟他们一起走吧 走吧
Go with them, quickly. Go.
我的死 比你更微不足道
My passing would be of even lesser concern than yours.
跟紧了
Stay close to heel.
我可不希望今晚就挂掉
I would not greet this night our last.
你疯了吗
Have you lost mind?!
卡斯特斯是来帮忙的
Castus came to aid!
他们这些家伙只帮该死的罗马人
He and his people aid only the fucking Romans!
我不知道你在说什么
I do not know of what you speak!
我酒醒了才发现兄弟们都走了
I awoke from drink to find my brothers gone.
他没参与这事
He had no hand in this.
艾力冈
Agron...
很多敌人过来了
More come.
我们必须走了
We must go.
你要是敢拿武器
Make attempt to seize weapon,
我就要了你的狗命
and I'll have your fucking life.
我们往山上撤
We move for the ridge.
快跑
Go!
这算什么计划啊
Not much of a plan, is it?
要是你有更好的 就说出来
If you hold better one, break words.
甘尼克斯
Gannicus...?
操 不是吧
Jupiter fuck me.
你怎么还在城里
Why are you yet within the city?
我正在逃跑的路上 罗马人就来了
I was upon path to leave it when the Romans came.
我不知道该怎么做
I did not know what to do.
甘尼克斯
Gannicus.
别哭了
Hold tears.
跟在我身边 千万别出声
Stay by my side, do not make a sound.
不然我们都会没命
Or see us all to the afterlife.
走
Go!
他们已经放弃了希望 开始烧城了
They abandon hope and burn the city.
叛贼们烧了粮仓
The rebels have set torch to horreum.
已派出三支百人队去…
Three centuries have been dispatched to quell
撤回来 按原计划前进
Recall them and move towards commanded path.
遵命
Imperator.
斯巴达克斯打算将我们的胜利果实化为灰烬
Spartacus attempts to turn victory into ash
你还要把军队撤回来
and you recall your men?
我的计划已经开始了
I have set plan to motion,
不能为此分心
and will not fall to distraction.
我们朝北门进军
We advance on northern gate!
列队
Form up!
跟上 别停下
Keep pace and do not pause!
快点 快点
Quickly! Hurry!
快走
Move!
多纳
Donar!
如果我就要死了
If I am to die,
生命的最后一刻能与你共度 真的很开心
it lifts heart to share final moment with you.
今晚很多人都死了
Many have fallen this night.
你不会死的
You shall not be among them.
跟上
Keep pace!
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus!
卡斯特斯
Castus.
你这该死的叛徒
You traitorous fuck.
他不知情
He knew nothing of this.
这是他自己的说法
By his own fucking tongue.
现在不是吵架的时候
This is not time to fall to quarrel!
绑住他的手 让他和大家一起出城
Bind his hands and see him through the gate with the others.
能打的留在后面掩护大家上山
Those who can fight take rear position as you take to the ridge!
带他走
Take him!
快走 不要回头
Move quickly, and do not turn back!
退后
Fall back!
护送他们出城
See all through the gate!
列队
Hold!
进攻
Attack!
我们必须关闭城门
We must seal gate behind us!
克雷斯
Oh, Crixus!
快撤
Go!
你要找的人
The man you seek.
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus!
抓住他
Seize him!
诸神居然会眷顾这群杂种
Even the gods grant aid to the fucking man.
他们早晚都要完蛋的
They but delay inevitable fall.
闩上城门 派兵驻守在这里
Bring ram to bear. Sentries to guard sundered gateway.
我们不追吗
We do not follow?
不是时候
In time.
全城搜查幸存的叛贼
Sweep the city for any of his followers that yet hold breath.
我们要处决他们 以庆祝此番大捷
So that we may rob them of it in celebration of glorious victory.
去你妈的 你这罗马混蛋
Fuck your little bird, you Roman cunt.
搜仔细了
Search everywhere.
全都找出来
Search them all!
让士兵们吃饭休息
Give men rest and meal.
明天一早就上山
Tomorrow's dawn shall see them march upon the ridge.
随从营地怎么办
What of followers' camp,
还有斯巴达克斯放出来的罗马人
and the Romans freed by Spartacus?
要让他们进城吗
Shall they be moved within safety of city walls?
只允许士兵进城
Only soldiers to be permitted within.
答不对口令的人
Any found absent proper watchword
格杀勿论
to be executed upon sight.
我可不希望满街叛贼的尸体
I would not have streets swollen with bodies errant rebels
给他们提供藏身之处
yet could secret themselves among.
不过少数人可以特殊对待
Though deserving few shall be granted consideration.
派人把这张单子上的人送到我宅子
Dispatch your men and see all upon this brought to villa.
遵命
Imperator.
你恢复原状了 恺撒
Ah, you return to form, Caesar.
这样子好多了
A most welcomed sight.
我刚刚还在赞赏他
I was only just praising him for his ability
居然能毫不费力地混进野狗群
to blend so effortlessly with a pack of savage dogs.
谁敢这样想呢
A thing of ill consideration,
如果不是克拉苏运筹帷幄的话
had Crassus not plucked scheme from fevered brain.
很抱歉我曾对此持怀疑态度
I am of regret to have ever laid doubt upon it.
听到希留爱沙山解放的消息
The Senate will be most pleased
元老院肯定倍感欣慰
to greet news of Sinuessa en Valle's liberation.
先别急着回罗马
Linger before return to Rome,
我们一起屠杀战俘以庆功
see it celebrated with Carnificina.
处决战俘
Executions?
黄昏开始
As night greets us.
我腾出了最好的宅子
I've set aside one of the finest villas
供你在庆功会之前休息沐浴
for you to rest and see yourself to bath, until such a time.
出乎我意料 不过感谢款待
A gesture unexpected, yet much appreciated.
谢谢
Gratitude.
瞧他趾高气昂的
Preening little fuck.
同感
A sentiment shared.
不过他代表了元老院
Yet he holds the ear of the Senate,
我要好好款待他
and I would see him well satisfied
让他回罗马后为我们的胜利美言几句
to further bolster tale of our victory carried back to Rome.
明眼人都能看出这算不上胜利
You speak again of victory shrouded from discerning eye.
斯巴达克斯还活着
Spartacus yet lives,
在米利亚峰的叛贼实力不容小觑
with considerable force aiding him upon Melia Ridge.
他们逃不出去的
There is no escape from the ridge.
无路可走
It stands impassable.
这种话 傻瓜葛雷博就说过
Words most likely broken by the fool Glaber
当时他把叛贼困在了维苏威火山上
when he had the rebel trapped upon Vesuvius.
你觉得我是傻瓜
You believe me the fool?
我相信你有无穷的谋略
I believe you a man of infinite plots,
戈尔迪之结 希腊神话中的一个难题
其巧妙连戈尔迪之结也难媲美
twisting upon themselves to shame Gordian knot.
多谢称赞
Praise well received.
别再想那些烦心事了
Now part mind from troubled thoughts,
我们回归正题
and allow it returned.
叛贼遭受致命打击
The rebellion has suffered fatal blow.
我要开庆功会 褒奖有功之人
At celebration I would honor hand that struck it.
真希望色雷斯人的首级
Would that the Thracian's head
插在长矛上 见证此等荣耀时刻
upon pike bore witness to such laurels.
保持耐心
Hold fast to patience,
耐心才使我们走到这一步
a thing that has propelled us to the ground we now stand upon.
不用多久 就能除掉斯巴达克斯
And in briefest passing shall claim Spartacus
以及追随他走向灭亡的人
and all those who yet follow the doom of his shadow.
这里没人
No one's here.
他们走了吗
They take leave?
还有人
Not all.
街上还有上千人
Thousands more swell in streets.
有人提到了胜利
The ones above spoke of victory,
我们死了很多人
great numbers lost to us.
更多的是诅咒斯巴达克斯逃了出去
Coupled with the curse that Spartacus yet eludes them.
想杀他可不容易
He is a troublesome man to kill.
我曾经试过
I have attempted it myself upon occasion.
诸神眷顾他
The gods favor him.
也会保佑我们
And bless us as well.
诸神冲我们撒尿 你还当成雨露
They piss upon us and you welcome it as cooling rain.
我们活下来了
We are alive.
因为诸神在指引你的手
Because they yet guide your hand.
我相信你能带我们逃出生天
One I have faith will see us from darkest hour.
真希望我也这样想
Would that I shared the same.
你以前给人包扎过
You have done this before.
我的主人经常打伤奴隶
My dominus inflicted many wounds upon his slaves.
我常常帮他们疗伤
I often tended their injuries.
那谁帮你疗伤
Who tended yours?
迪欧特莫斯待我很好
Diotimus showed a kindness.
现在呢
Did he now?
他待我像哥哥一样
He stood as a brother to me.
抱歉
Apologies.
你杀死了夺走他生命的人
You struck down the man that took his life.
那个多年以来
The man that took my own,
慢慢侵蚀我生命的人
a small piece at a time over span of years.
但愿有所改变吧
Would that it had made difference.
你改变了一切
You have made all in the world.
站住
Hold!
给她松绑
See her hands freed of bond.
她不是奴隶
This woman stands no fucking slave.
我见过你
I know you.
不是吗
Do I not?
你看到的我是另一副样子
You have laid eyes upon distorted reflection of the man before you.
我潜伏在叛贼之中
I was secreted among the rebels,
满脸胡子 满口谎言
beard upon cheek and lies upon tongue.
你站在克雷斯那帮禽兽一边
You stood with Crixus and his animals
任由他们屠杀已沦为奴隶的我们
as they slaughtered my people, bound in chains.
我深表遗憾
A deed of much regret.
但也只能如此
Yet born of necessity.
在说服西利西亚人反戈之前 我不能暴露
I could not risk discovery short of turning the Cilicians to our cause.
战争中 一切都是为了生存
In war, one does what one must to survive.
感同身受
A burden not unfamiliar.
克拉苏有吩咐
Crassus would have word.
在你曾经的家中安排了一顿盛宴
You are to be fed proper meal and bathed in rosewater,
还有玫瑰花浴
in the villa you once called home.
来吧
Come.
抱歉
Apologies.
我没想吓你
I did not move to frighten.
最近的事情让我精神紧张
Recent events set nerves to edge.
不要再担忧了
See grave concern give way.
城已攻占
The city is taken,
我毫发无伤
and I stand unscathed.
伟大的胜利
A great victory.
我希望你能
One whose celebration,
一起参加庆功大会
I would have you share in.
我可以留在您这儿
I am to stay here, with you?
你不高兴吗
Would you stand pleased by it?
高兴得无以言表
Beyond the telling of words.
你应该高兴才对 怎么流泪了
There is no cause for tears on such a day.
这是高兴的泪水
They are of joy,
为我终于能摆脱随从营地
to find myself delivered from followers' camp.
摆脱
Delivered?
有这么不开心吗
Has it grown so unpleasant?
难以忍受
Unbearably so...
是我的错
The fault is mine.
萨比努斯的死让我很悲伤
I lay upon Kore heavy burden,
我对克芮倾诉太多
of lending ear to my grief
给了她很大的精神负担
in the passing of Sabinus.
是我造成的
And my hand in it.
当命运召唤之时
A man does what is required,
你尽到了责任
when fate calls upon him.
军令如山
As all soldiers must.
克芮给我的安慰
Kore served greater comfort
是您难以想象的
than you will ever know.
就怕我的痛苦
Yet I fear my pain has,
给她造成了太大的压力
pressed hard against her.
但愿你足够坚强 不要垮掉
I pray you are not too delicate to bear such weight.
我虽然不是战士
I stand no soldier in this conflict.
但该我做的我绝不逃避
Yet I too shall do what I must.
感激不尽
I am forever grateful.
去准备一下酒和食物
See wine and food prepared.
遵命 主人
Yes, Dominus.
这场战争永远地改变了她
This war has forever changed her.
改变的不止是她一个人
She does not stand alone is such regard.
也同样磨砺了我
I am but hardened by it,
使我教训深刻
and the lessons it has taught.
我本来担心十一抽杀
I had thought decimation
有可能让你丧失理性
in threat of pulling you from reason.
可你如凤凰涅槃
Yet you rise like the phoenix,
眼中充满火焰
the fire of purpose filling eye.
不久你便能官复原职 代我行使权力
And soon shall take your place again as my word and my will.
不久
Soon?
您还没有恢复我的职位吗
You did not summon to reinstate me into the legion?
我安排你负责主持屠杀战俘一事
I would have you present carnificina for the men.
当着军团的面提升士气
It will elevate you in the eyes of the legion
你便能出出风头
to be seen in such giving spirit.
为你重新掌握军权铺平道路
And ease the way for you to again assume command.
承蒙关照
A privilege then.
这也是称颂您此次大捷的好机会
And opportunity to honor you and your triumph.
你搞错了
You mistake intent.
我们要宣扬的是恺撒
We shall honor Caesar as the victor.
我跟他向来不和
There is no love lost between us.
当然了 等我掌权 他很适合在…
Surely there must be more fitting service that I might
聪明人懂得如何化敌为友
A shrewd man turns rival to valued ally.
恺撒背负家族的传奇名号
Caesar is blessed with storied name,
终有一天他的成就堪与日月争辉
and shall one day rise to shame the very sun.
与他交好
Make peace,
到时候你自然受益无穷
and bask in glorious light.
他会得到应有的尊重
He shall be awarded all respect deserved.
很多孩子投身战场
Many a boy may enter a war.
但到了最后
Yet at it's end,
走出来的只有男人
only a man will emerge.
很高兴你能成为这样的人
It warms my heart to see you become one.
是您造就了我
I am what you have made me.
来的人更多了
More soldiers return.
他们正在拆开木板到处搜索
They pry wood and beams searching for vermin.
如果我们不走 他们能发现我们吗
If we stay, will they not find us?
当然
They will.
我们就坐以待毙吗
Is there nothing we can do?
有一件事可以做
There is but one thing.
祈祷
Pray.
如果回来的人不是我
If any but my visage return,
你就自刎
take your life.
比起他们的手段 这是最好的结局
It will be a kindness in comparison to what they will do to you.
叛贼 在这里
Rebel! Here!
逮住他了
I got him!
我开始相信你说的神了
I begin to believe in your gods.
看看他们能眷顾我们多久吧
Let us see how far they will take us.
白葡萄酒
Falernian.
这酒让我想起你的滋味
A taste I recall you favor.
这是给你父亲准备的
It is for your father.
他拥有的太多了
As are many things.
统帅有很多事情要考虑
The Imperator has much pressing upon mind.
给他增添烦恼
Laying more upon it
无异于往胸口插刀子
would only serve to open grievous wound.
多年来我对你的关心难道毫无意义吗
Do all the years I have cared for you stand for nothing?
你给了我极大的抚慰
They have brought me greatest comfort.
你要是离开我们家
It would sadden heart,
我该有多么伤心
to see you turned from our house.
又或者你受到最残酷的惩罚
Or set to cruelest punishment...
要是让他知道你为了安慰我
If he ever learned how you willingly
主动献身的那股殷勤劲…
gave yourself to me in attempt to ease my pain.
说错一个字
If errant word falls from mouth,
就等着受苦吧
only suffering will follow them.
动手的不是统帅
At the hands of the Imperator.
就是我
Or my own.
下次我就不会这么温柔了
And I will not be as gentle next time.
你真美
You stand a vision.
堪比我的爱妻
One to rival my own beloved wife.
恢复原来的样子 真像做梦
It is as a dream, to be resurrected so.
来吧
Come.
克拉苏等着你
Crassus awaits your company.
遵照您的指示
She has been prepared,
她准备好了
as commanded.
上次见面
When last I laid eyes,
你就像一尊
you appeared as defiled effigy,
因战祸而蒙尘的雕像
marred by calamity of war.
现在恢复了维纳斯般的美貌
Now restored to graven image of Venus herself.
感谢您
Gratitude.
为您所做的一切
For all that you have done.
如果没有别的事
I would take my leave,
我告退了
if I am of no further use.
在庆功宴前先回趟房间
Fall to your chambers in advance of celebration.
有份礼物等着你
You shall find welcomed gifts,
这是你应得的
most deserved.
你们要庆功
You hold celebration?
屠杀战俘
Carnificina.
庆祝我们战胜了叛贼
In honor of our victory against the rebel king.
请原谅
Apologies.
恐怕我还打不起精神
I fear I am not yet of strength
我没指望你会出席
I did not imagine you would be of attendance.
你能活着就是万幸了
It is a blessing you yet draw breath.
斯巴达克斯手下留情 对吧
One bestowed by Spartacus himself, was it not?
正如我告诉您的
As I have told you,
我只为了解救我的人民
I exchanged words with the man only in hope
和他说过几句话
of sparing what remained of my people.
我认为这没错
Know that I find no fault in it.
携雨之使者的传奇
The whole of Rome echoes with
在整个罗马传得天花乱坠
inflated legend of the Bringer of Rain.
我希望听听真实的故事
I would hear air filled with truer tale,
关于斯巴达克斯的说法
of Spartacus the man.
我只是他的俘虏
I knew him only as captor.
我不是在套你话
I do not move to trap you.
我渴望听到对这位罕见敌手的中肯评价
I but crave honest appraisal of worthy adversary.
我们很快要在战场上见面了
One I shall soon meet upon field of battle.
斯巴达克斯似乎
Spartacus seems...
不是人们想象中的野兽
not the beast, one would form thought of.
没有尖牙利爪 那他有什么呢
And in place of horns and sharpened claw?
一颗受伤的心
A wounded heart.
讨回公道的渴望
Yearning to balance scale.
我知道他妻子的事
I know of his wife,
也知道他渴望复仇
and his thirst to avenge her death.
他并非嗜血成性
No he is not consumed by a thirst for blood.
也许他曾经是
Perhaps he stood as such once,
但现在
yet now...
他为自己的信念而战
he fights for what he believes is just.
没什么比这更危险的了
There is no cause more dangerous.
他不会停下脚步
He will not stop.
我想他不会 即使他自己想
I do not believe he could, even if he so wished it.
这么说他和我一样
Then he and I stand the same.
都觉得自己是英雄
Each believes himself the hero,
对方是恶人
the other villain.
历史会证明谁对谁错
It is for history to decide who is mistaken.
在此之前 我们都要在命运舞台上各饰其角
Until such a day,we shall play our parts upon fortune's stage.
我们都要如此
As each of us must.
城归您了 伟大的克拉苏
The city is yours, mighty Crassus!
我来拿说好的奖赏
I would see to agreed upon price
因为罗马收复失地有我的功劳
for aiding in its return to Roman hands.
您和这些混账做了交易
You set bargain with this fucking shit?
代价沉重啊
One of gravest cost.
不要出现在我面前了
See yourself far from my presence.
否则要你们看不到明天的太阳
Or witness rise of morning sun from the shores of the afterlife.
我今晚便如您所愿
I will take most welcomed leave by night's end.
带着应得的奖励离开
With all that I have been promised.
我可是罗马人
I am a Roman.
你帮了我们的敌人
One that gave aid to our enemy,
无论是何原因
for whatever the reason.
你不能这么做
You cannot do this.
事情已经定了
It is already done.
遵守诺言的人如今很少见了
It is the rarest of things, to see a man that honors his words.
要是过了时间还不走
Stay beyond agreed upon hour,
你就会看到我是怎么遵守诺言的
and you shall know the bitter truth of it.
愿诸神给予你应得的赏赐
May the gods grant all that you deserve.
伟大的克拉苏
mighty Crassus.
就像他们对待我赫拉克里奥
As they have granted Heracleo.
来吧 亲爱的
Come, my love.
城墙之外有数不尽的奇观
There are many wonders beyond these walls
我盼着你能见识
I long for you to see.
你想谈谈吗
You wish to break words?
提比略
Tiberius.
真令人欣慰
It warms heart,
看到你从最近的不幸中走出来
to see you recovered from your recent misfortunes.
来 喝酒 让我们好好…
Come, drink wine, let us regail
我可没有时间陪你
My time is of short offering.
我忙着准备你的庆功会
I am taken with preparing celebration in your honor.
谢谢你的付出
Gratitude for the effort.
到时候你想来点什么呢
Is there anything you desire towards it?
蜂蜜酒
Honeyed wine?
烤野猪
Roasted boar?
来自波塞冬花园的牡蛎
Oysters plucked from Poseidon's garden?
我只是想表达一下对你的敬意
I would merely attempt to honor you with gift.
就像你对我一样
As you honor me.
这是坎莎拉
This is Canthara.
出生于尼罗河东岸
Born east of the Nile,
不过别拿这个说她
but do not judge her for it...
随从不能进城
Followers are not allowed within city walls.
这是你父亲的礼物
It is a gift from your father.
我愿意和你分享
One I would share.
是他命令你这么做的吗
Did he command you to do this?
就像命令我称颂你一样
As he commanded me to pay tribute to you?
还是回到我身边吧
Return to more willing flesh.
这孩子更喜欢辩论 而不是上床
The boy favors contention over cunt.
我喜欢事实
I but favor truth.
统帅希望我们和平相处
The Imperator would see us to common ground.
可你我隔阂甚大
I find us far removed.
简直是云泥之别
As mortal from a god.
一人面对一小撮叛贼
One set upon a small band of rebels
有百人队的支持
with support of a century,
却丢盔弃甲 夺命而逃
lost his sword, turned heel and fled.
而另一人 孤身闯虎穴
While the other, strolled into the jaws of the beast.
手无寸铁 仅凭如簧巧舌
Absent weapon, and brought down
拿下了一座城池
an entire city with but cunning and silver tongue.
想想吧
Refresh mind.
你是哪一个
Which do you stand?
终有一日 我能官复原职
Upon a day my title shall be returned to me.
把你踩在脚下…
And place you beneath heel
我耽误你太久了 你还有要务在身
I have delayed you too long from pressing charge.
你做的这件事
And the opportunity it brings,
多少能赢得一点点
to earn small sum of respect
我们这些小兵的尊重呢
from those of us that stand as soldiers.
还有 提比略
Oh, and Tiberius?
别忘了牡蛎
Oysters.
街上防守严密
The streets stand too swollen.
只在屋顶上行动是没法出城的
And rooftops alone will not carry us free of the city.
甘尼克斯
Gannicus...
站住
Halt.
让开
Part way.
那叛徒还没死
The traitor yet lives.
我的行动受你们统帅的保护
I move beneath protection of your Imperator.
你的船不在这个方向
Your ship stands in opposing direction.
我要向刚收到的宝贝
I would present precious bounty
表达一下喜爱之情
with offering of affection,
然后再回海上去
before taking to unforgiving sea.
放他们过去
Let them pass.
你看我就像看怪物
You look upon me as a monster.
觉得我配不上你是吗
Yet am I not more desirable fate?
可你丈夫死了
With husband fallen to the afterlife,
跟着罗马人 你又能过上怎样的生活
what life would you have among the Romans?
你只是女人
You are a woman.
对他们来说跟奴隶差不多
No better than a slave to them.
我可是很看重你的
I bestow loftier consideration.
我绝不会像克拉苏那样
I would never bargain you off,
把你卖掉
as Crassus has done.
也不会把你关在笼子里
Nor would I lock you in a cage
让他们轮流玩
and pass you about,
虽然我手下希望我这样做
as my men would have me do.
不会
No...
你会站在我身边
you shall stand beside me,
成为海上的王后
a queen upon the sea.
我最贵重的珍宝
My greatest treasure.
见到我们的人
And all who cross our path
都会知道你属于我
shall know that you are mine.
不要
No!
赫拉克里奥 不
Heracleo, no!
很抱歉要让你吃点苦头 亲爱的
Apologies for the pain I cause, my love.
不 不
No, no!
以后都不会这么痛苦了
That is the worst if it my love.
我看不是
I do not believe it so.
看你还活着 真令人振奋 朋友
It lifts spirits to see you alive,my friend.
我的很多兄弟就没这个运气了
Many of my brothers did not fare as well.
这是不可避免的
An act born of necessity,
我也很难过啊
and raised with heavy heart.
我很欣赏斯巴达克斯大王和他的兄弟
I much liked King Spartacus and his companions...
大部分吧
Well, most of them.
可我面临一个选择
Yet I was given a choice
是荣华富贵还是凄惨死去
between a wealthy life, or die a merciless death.
像我这种人 这根本没得选
Which to a man of my sort, is no choice at all.
我知道你怎么想
I know what thoughts pass through mind.
我们都是该死的西利西亚人
That we are but shit-eating Cilicians,
哪能跟竞技场之神相提并论
no match for a god of the arena.
也许不假 朋友
Perhaps this is true, my friend.
也许我死之前 我的剑会割开你女人的喉咙
Perhaps my sword will find your woman's throat, before I fall.
眼下这种状况
A thing you must appreciate
你要理解我才是
in such a delicate situation.
她不是我的女人
She is not my woman.
希贝儿
Sibyl!
看来这小丫头对你很重要嘛
So you do care for the little one, huh?
不过很遗憾 你害死她了
But it's a pity now that you have killed her.
不要
No!
你受伤了吗
You are hurt?
我们快走 免得被发现
We must move quickly before we are discovered.
莱塔呢
What of Laeta?
她怎么了
What of her?
我们不能丢下她
We cannot leave her.
她是罗马人
She stands Roman.
不能让人看到她和我们一起
She won't be seen with us.
我现在只是奴隶
I stand nothing but a slave.
跟你们过去一样
As you once did.
你鼓舞士气可真有一套 克拉苏
You are truly gifted at motivating your men, Crassus.
这是伟大领袖的特质
As all great leaders must be.
这话别传到元老院去了
Do not allow the Senate to hear you describe me as such.
他们也许会把你五马分尸
They might well tear you asunder in like fashion.
别担心这些
Give no worry to such thought.
你击退了斯巴达克斯
You shall gain their gratitude
他们必定很感谢你
in blow struck against Spartacus,
你还让希留爱沙山的市民
and return of Sinuessa en Valle to
又回到了他们的家园
rightful embrace of its citizens.
这才刚开始呢
We've just begun!
抱歉 我要更正你的话
Apologies, but I must serve correction.
这座美丽城市的市民
The citizens of this fair city
全都惨死于暴怒的叛贼之手
were all laid to grass by rebellion's fury.
并非全部
Not all.
所有贵族都死了
All of note.
市政官的妻子呢
What of the Aedile's wife?
她走了 永远不会回来
She has left these walls, never to return.
莫非你要占有这座城吗
You would claim entire fucking city for yourself?
聪明人打仗不只是为了荣誉
A wise man does not fight for glory alone.
元老院绝不会轻易答应如此贪婪的要求
The Senate will not easily swallow bitter news of such greed.
贪婪无非是嫉妒之人对雄心壮志的说法
Greed is but a word jealous men inflict upon the ambitious.
他们只能任其自然
They will be made to see past it
将这一战利品赐给我们
and oblige us in the spoils of war.
我们
Us?
我当然要与你共享了
I would share in good fortune, of course.
也许你愿意得到现在住的宅子
Perhaps the villa you now occupy
还有港口的一部分税收
and a portion of the taxes levied upon port?
只要有人能说服元老院
If the Senate could be persuaded that we are
答应我们的正当要求
deserving of such bold claim?
我们完成了不可能的任务
We have done the impossible.
当然值得奖励
Surely we should be rewarded for it.
最后一份血之献礼
Let us have final tribute of blood,
向盖乌斯•尤利乌斯•恺撒致敬
in honor of Gaius Julius Caesar!
恺撒
Caesar!
该死的罗马懦夫
Roman fucking cowards.
要是拿着剑来一场公平决斗
Shit running your leg in thought of giving sword
你们就屁滚尿流了
and proper contest.
如果有这样的机会 你会怎么做 野蛮人
And what would you do if graced with such opportunity, savage?
受到这样的待遇 我万分感谢
Such spectacle is deeply appreciated.
要是斯巴达克斯伏法那就更妙了
Yet the fall of Spartacus greeted more so.
屠杀大戏要结束了
Carnificina comes to an end.
马上就轮到叛贼头子
The rebel king to soon follow.
统帅
Imperator.
贵宾们
Honored guests.
今天我们齐聚此处
We come this day to praise a man
称颂一位出类拔萃的英雄
considered above all others.
他肯定有诸神的庇佑
A man possessed of such good fortune
否则怎能有如此好的运气
that he must indeed be blessed by the gods themselves.
屠杀战俘有个传统
In storied tradition of Carnificina,
最后一杀代表了胜利之巅
the ultimate kill signifies pinnacle of victory.
我们是否应当把最后一击的荣耀交给恺撒
Shall we award Caesar the privilege of delivering fated blow,
让他使用打仗所用的利剑 而不是…
with sword of steel in a war he began with but...
如簧巧舌
tongue of silver?
恺撒 恺撒
Caesar! Caesar!
你的发言真是深思熟虑
You choose your words with care.
无论谁身在此位 都应当如此
As all who must, in such position.
这个人的死 不是恺撒的荣耀
This man shall fall not in honor of Caesar.
也不是伟大的克拉苏家族的荣耀
Nor the great House of Crassus.
他的死 是伟大罗马的荣耀
He shall fall in honor of the glory of Rome!
罗马万岁
Glory of Rome!
杀了他
Kill him!
住手
Hold!
这是神的旨意
It is the will of the gods,
诸神要这头野兽挣脱镣铐
that this beast shall see himself free of shackles.
让我得以证明我实至名归
So that I may prove myself worthy of the praise
不负我们的统帅 以及…
bestowed upon me by our Imperator...
他儿子的好意
and his boy.
那就来吧
Come then.
让我们看看你们叛贼有什么本事
Let us see what challenge your rebellion truly offers.
他们在庆祝吗
They hold celebration?
处决你们当中还幸存的人
Executions, for those among you yet of this world.
总有一天 我要让他们血债血偿
I will have blood in their name, upon a day.
照我说的 尽量走小巷或人少的街道
Stay to the alleys and lesser streets as I guide.
你才有可能活到那一天
And perhaps live to see it so.
如果叛贼都像此人这么厉害
If this man stands for all of the rebellion,
那我们可能庆祝得太早了
celebration may hold premature.
这个人的死
Let this man's death serve as
是斯巴达克斯本人
harbinger for the fate
即将遭受同样下场的先兆
that we shall inflict upon Spartacus himself!
打得好 兄弟
Well fought, brother.
吃屎去吧 罗马狗
Swallow cock, you Roman shit.
瞧啊
Behold!
他们最伟大的战士也因惧怕恺撒而自杀了
Their greatest warriors take their own lives in fear of Caesar!
恺撒
Caesar!
我们出不去了
We will not make it.
你会骑马吗
Can you ride?
我骑过
I've seen it done.
跟紧点
Stay close.
我们不会回来救你的
We will not turn back for you.
你站住
You there.
赫拉克里奥不是只要一个女人吗
I thought Heracleo granted but one woman.
另外这个哪儿来的
Where did he come by this one?
跑
Go!
去敲警钟 一帮废物
Sound the alarm, you worthless shits!
关闭城门
Close gate!
叛贼逃跑了 守住城门
The rebel escapes! Man the gate!
为什么我们的军队不追击
Why do we not move after him?
非得让我恺撒冒生命危险亲手杀死每个叛贼吗
Must Julius fucking Caesar risk life to kill every last Rebel himself?
夜晚上山 对我军不利
To attempt the ridge at night would see us to disadvantage.
到了早上 他就和斯巴达克斯
And by morning he will be to the wind with Spartacus
还有你放走的那帮叛贼会合了
and the rest of his rebel horde you allowed to escape.
我不是放他们走 是给了他们虚无的希望
I have allowed nothing but the illusion of hope.
日升之时 我军将在十一抽杀律的威胁下
When sun breaks my legions shall begin final march,
开始全面围剿叛贼
spurred by dread of decimation
他们渴望得到你昨晚所拥有的那种荣耀
and dreams of glory sparked by celebration in your honor.
斯巴达克斯不是傻子
Spartacus is no fool.
你觉得他会在大风雪中
You expect him to wait in driven snow,
等你到来 给他致命一击吗
for you to arrive and announce his end?
那正是我所期待的
That is exactly what I expect.
我们不能待在这里
We cannot remain here.
那你想怎么样
What would you have us do?
长出翅膀 飞到太阳神阿波罗那里
Sprout wings and soar towards warming
投向他温暖的怀抱吗
embrace of fucking Apollo?
我们应该回去 夺回希留爱沙
We should turn and retake Sinuessa.
那座城已经陷落
The city is lost.
要是我们不行动 我们也完蛋了
As we shall be, if we do not act.
我操
Fuck the gods.
我还以为就我命硬呢
And I believed myself a difficult man to kill.
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus!
你给我们带来了俘虏
You bring us a prisoner.
莱塔现在跟你我一样
Laeta now stands as you or I,
被共和国踩在脚下
beneath heel of Republic.
好好照顾的话
She may yet live,
她也许能活
if her wounds are tended.
救活她
See it done.
卢戈
Lugo.
我们这些人都还活着 真是奇迹
It is miracle any of us before you yet draw breath.
诸神肯定听到了我们的祈祷
The gods themselves must have taken note of delivered prayer,
改变了我们的命运
in order to see us from certain end.
恐怕只是时间问题
I fear they have but delayed it.
这怎么可能
How is such a thing possible?
对共和国最富有的人来说 没什么不可能
Nothing is beyond reach for the richest man in the Republic.
克拉苏
Crassus.
他一直想把我们困在山上
It was always his intention, to trap us upon this ridge.
他必定率军出城向我们后方进攻
He will march from the city with his armies behind us.
等他到来
And when he comes...
死亡也随之降临
death shall follow in his wake.